hello and welcome it's December 13th
2024 we're in active inference guest
stream
93.1 with Nim Deus we're going to be
discussing a paper we wrote together
enhancing populationbased search with
active inference so thank you n for
joining looking forward to your
presentation and the discussion my
pleasure thank you then very happy to be
here and to share this joint work we did
together a few months ago uh perhaps I
could give a brief um you know
background information about how this
work came to be uh we did a podcast
together and we had a few Chats on on
Discord about active inference and it
was actually a way you used to explain
active inference you said um that it's
um like the sense of touch for
example uh wouldn't be really active
unless you you move your hand you know
to really discover the texture and it's
the idea that indeed um you know
perception is not a passive process
where just receiving data and processing
it uh it's that agents have um an intent
right and this is something that
meditators can also um you know um
experience is that uh even seeing you
know site uh if you are really empty
inside wouldn't really be active unless
you have some intent you know so uh I
thought about this in the context of um
a class of um multi-agent systems that
are uh used for optimization problems so
perhaps I'll give an overview of our our
work so this is a kind of um metah
aristic methods that I used to solve all
sorts of optimization problems uh but we
mainly focus on combinatorial
optimization so uh problems in graphs
typically and they use a population of
agents to uh you know explore different
uh solution
paths and one one common feature as I
will highlight later of these methods is
that they just like you know the the the
the naive perception we have of uh you
know how how um even humans perceive is
that they they consider that these
agents have only reactive responses to
the data they discover in the the
environment uh we'll see it in more
details later when I do a brief
literature review and
so uh we try to incorporate predictive
modeling giving these agents an intent
which is to to reduce their surprise uh
and also update their belief we'll talk
about that as well uh so the idea is to
minimize the difference between uh the
outcomes they they observe and what they
expect and we try to integrate this to
this class of methods known as
population based search methods with an
instantiation on uh one method called uh
the uh ant colony optimization that's
also inspired by you Danielle and your
background uh working with ants and so
uh this will be applied to uh a problem
which I think is U famous enough so I
don't have to give a very detailed um
explanation of it but perhaps for um
people who are not familiar with the
traveling salesman problem I will
briefly explain it with this uh little
app we put together for the paper so
it's a problem in graphs where you have
typically
um set of cities or locations uh the
problem consists in finding a route that
visits all cities and goes back to your
initial Point okay now with this kind of
problems
um there are two classes typically uh
problems in P which can be solved in
polinomial time one example would be
finding the shortest route from one
point to the other that is very easy to
solve and it remains easy even for very
large scale uh graphs very large numbers
of cities but this problem the traveling
salesman problem the idea of visiting
all cities and going back to your
initial Point happens to be uh you know
in in a different class NP so it is as
hard as any computational problem you
can think of and here again the the
difficulty comes with with scale it's
that U we don't
have pretty much uh we not have a a
better method than you know exhaustively
uh listing all parts so uh there are
approximate solution methods known as
heuristics and metah heuristics a very
simple one a very intuitive one could be
to visit the nearest city from your
starting point and repeat this process
um until you go back to your initial
point so this is known as uh the nearest
neighbor um heuristic so here I would
start for example from this one go to
the next one next one next one next one
and then with this you can get stuck in
in very bad you know um branches of the
the tree of possible solutions for
example if the last city is very far
here right you need to uh waste a lot of
uh you know uh distance in in in your
solution so nearest neighbor is not that
great and there are methods that try to
improve on it uh one of them is the one
we will um discuss in this presentation
the art colon optimization method so as
I was saying it's part of a large class
of U methods known as populationbased
search metah eristics uh they are uh
typically uh nature inspired or biology
inspired but one very good point you
raised Daniel is that uh well can there
be anything that is not nature inspired
that's a a good question to to ponder in
any case these are inspired by you know
phenomena in nature um initially I think
the the first method in this in this
class
uh was invented in the 70s it's the
genetic algorithm that is inspired by
Evolution and here again there would be
interesting Bridges with um active
inference ant colony optimization is
also one of the the most successful and
oldest but then there was a deluge of uh
you know nature inspired methods for
about 30 years uh anything from honey
bees to uh cuu to wolves to Lions
Dolphins what have you even the way jazz
players human jazz players uh you know
synchronize when they they improvise uh
were used as inspiration for these
methods um and just as a fun fact um
artificial neural networks were
considered as part of this class of
methods um up until the mid 2000s when I
was an undergrad myself and they were
usually listed in um you know textbooks
like the two have cited here among these
population-based metah aristic before
taking you know life on their own uh but
because of this you know uh
very very large number of of methods
that offer very little Innovation uh
some authors notably um kenet Sanson
here with this important paper that uh
was published in
2013 called for you know uh a stop to to
to uh these very superficial you know uh
improvements in Innovations just taking
inspiration from the next you know
natural process and to go back to more
abstract ways of seeing these methods
uh so more abstractly we can break down
these populationbased uh search methods
in um you
know by the fact that they have these
three characteristics first there is of
course a population of agents that
cooperate so each one of them is going
to explore some solution paths since
exploring you know uh exhaustively
exploring the whole tree of of possible
solutions is not feasible uh agents
would have some some some way to to
explore Solutions themselves and they're
going to cooperate share
information uh another common
characteristics of these methods is that
uh they they usually um include self-
adaptation the the agents respond to
their environment and we come back to
respond later uh and modify their you
know their search strategy accordingly
and there is also competition among the
the solutions discovered so far by the
population of agents and we keep the
best uh you know subset of solutions so
if we see it this
way
um many of the you
know nature inspired methods we we have
here come down to just ways to you know
um Define these three characteristics
right but one common thing among all
methods pretty much is that they all
assume and I think it's a common bias we
have in in designing um algorithms and
multi-agent systems is that we assume
that agents passively receive
information and in the way they they
retrieve this information they have no
no intent right and so that's one thing
that we could possibly uh you know
explore as a way to improve these
metalistics
particularly ant colony
optimization so to to present the the
method briefly the population is a
population inspired by the behavior of
ants each uh you know uh agent would be
um
exploring one possible uh you know uh
path uh of solutions uh so it mimic how
how aunts behave in that U once uh an
aunt or agent finds a promising path
they're going to leave a trail of
feromon that is going to be more and
more attractive to other agents as you
know as uh as it is explored by by more
more ants Okay so the feromon system
system is a way for agents to leave
information for for for others and uh
progressively reinforce you know the
best
Solutions and so uh one subtlty is that
um there's also phenomenon of
evaporation of these um thermals as
would happen naturally in fact uh so
that we don't get stuck in in local
Minima and that uh you know we forget
bad Solutions over time
and the choice of the the next node to
explore
in the application to the traveling Sal
problem for example would be based on uh
what what trail of herone um other ants
left and also the intrinsic potential of
that that that choice uh you know in in
finding uh a minimum length uh traveling
route
okay and so this is the basic ant colony
optimization but here again as you can
see agents are considered to be passive
you know um receptors VI it of pheromone
or information in general and they don't
have any any intent in their in their
exploration and so ant colon
optimization was a very successful
method for the traveling sasma problem
up until very recently now there are
better uh you know approximate
methods
and as I was briefly explaining the way
the ants are going to collectively uh
construct a good route would be that
each Aunt visits node by node until it
completes uh one tour and the the most
promising tours are going to to have you
know the most promising uh edges in fact
between between notes are going to have
a higher concentration of fomon over
time and uh at the end we keep the best
encountered Solution by the the
population as a whole
now on the other hand active inference
and here I speak under your your
supervision Danielle um it's a shift in
the way we we view uh you know
perception um itself from uh just
reacting to to data that is assumed to
be received passively to uh considering
that agents have uh an intent which is
uh to to to predict some some outcome
and also minimize their their their
surprise
um when encountering you know um real
outcomes the surprise compared to what
they have predicted right so there could
be U interesting discussions to be to to
be had about the the statistical mod the
statistical model to use for uh you know
modeling um this prediction are also the
surprise but uh speaking again
abstractly and at a high level um here
we assume that agents anticipate some
future state
they build a belief about the current uh
you know observations they are they're
making and the choices they make in the
future are not just based on you know
the immediate data they receive but also
on this belief that they have built uh
and uh overall that the objective would
be to min minimize free energy and so
the way we implemented this in um ant
colony
optimization is that it is going to to
change the way we calculate the not
selection prob which was initially just
based on mly on pheromones and here
we're going to to balance U the feromon
level available in that in that choice
with the the total distance of the the
the rout built so far and also the
current belief of the the the agent the
aunt that is exploring it we also have a
calculation of free
energy the typical way with uh the logs
of B in this
case and we will adjust the belief or
confidence level of the the an in its
current exploration part um based
on the the length of the current path
compared to the best path encountered so
far by the whole population okay and
then the the feron would be updated
based on uh well or the typical way
based on the the the length of a current
path and so we're going to integrate
this in the typical you know uh scheme
for um Anon optimization with these
changes in the way we we update
um the way we we calculate sorry the
probability of selecting the next
node so the typical um steps would be
that uh we start with some uniform
feromon levels for all choic
um the the the ant each one of them is
going to to to update its belief based
on its current exploration we calculate
the the free energy for each agent and
then we're going to iteratively um
update both the beliefs and the the you
know the best encountered Solutions
and at the end we keep the the the best
route discovered by the the the
population and here again there would be
some adjustment to to be made about you
know uh the number of um you know agents
in the population that you would like to
consider the amount of computation time
that you give yourself that could more
or less influence the the quality of the
uh you know the resulting Solutions but
uh again abstractly this is how we would
uh structure the the algorithm and so we
have applied this to the traveling
salesman problem the problem I have
presented here let me clear them map to
to take another
example and we compare um this you know
enhanced an Colony optimization as we
call it or active an Colony optimization
with both basic Anolon optimization and
uh you know the the the nearest neighbor
the very naive aristic as uh
Baseline so we took random symmetric
graphs of increasing um
sizes um and one interesting thing we
found well we found a few interesting um
things it's that first um this simple
change in the way you you calculate the
the probability of selecting the next
node does improve um the the quality of
the the results significantly uh so it
does give you shorter um roots on
average than uh basic ant colony optim
optimization I don't know if we can see
it already example let's try so I we run
the basic AR Colony optimization
here we
find a root of this length 11
1286 with active
inference seems to be the same so maybe
we should add more notes and here again
the the difference is really uh only
appears when you have large enough
graphs and complex enough graphs let's
try again with this one maybe will'll be
luckier I I'll give a comment on that
I'll give a comment on that while you're
running the different ones yeah yeah
this and this gives possibly an
interesting uh case so first off there's
many graphs where a number of heris sixs
could and would and should Converge on
the same simple output so there's never
any wrong with running multiple uh
parallel metah eristics and so I was
seeing that free energy calculation as
counteracting with an entropic Force the
convergent tendency of the attractive
pherone so you have the ants laying down
phermones based upon shorter paths and
prior success and then there's this kind
of expansive Force that's keeping an
additional variance element around and
so it's kind of like the ball is is
rolling to the bottom of the hill that's
the standard ant colony optimization and
then the free energy is in keeping it a
little bit off the bottom so then
looking at a huge numbers of replicates
for graphs it was interesting that on
many cases it would do a tiny bit
worse but then in several cases keeping
it lifted off the ground with that
entropic force would actually let it
explore a totally different neighborhood
and find vastly better Solutions so that
that that overall
it found shorter paths but that it found
basically either the same or almost the
same in most cases and then a few
situations where I found something that
was hugely
shorter well well I have two two two
comments on this uh that was actually
going to be my my conclusion for for
this presentation uh the way I see it is
that uh at this point it is interesting
and useful to to do applied work like we
do here to to show imp is that the
simple you know shift in the way you you
you define the behavior of your agents
does improve things empirically and here
we have an improvement actually with
this this graph so uh it is actually
significant uh basic ant colony gives
us something like
174 and we get 16 something with um
active inference so there is definitely
value in in applied work like this and
what I would be interested in exploring
would be um whether this also replicates
for you know other population based
metalistics notably genetic algorithms
or uh you know other approaches
simulated and healing Etc uh but uh the
point you raise um well it's little
beyond my my understanding of of active
active inference to be honest but I
think there is definitely need for more
theoretical grounding and it sounds very
interesting it's that um active
inference just this this change in the
way you calculate probability can allow
you to Escape right uh Minima that are
not that are not that promising uh so
that would be definitely needed at some
point uh of course when and if we get uh
promising results with with other
methods is to justify it theoretically
because right now it's just based on you
know um intuition uh indeed agents uh
can can be improved by by by having you
know this this intent in their
exploration but uh I would be very
interested in reading more you know
about um the relationship with entropy
and how it can you know be seen in the
the graph of you know the the tree of of
possible solutions uh that's one point
and the second one is that uh
indeed the the complexity of the the
graph matters of course but even in the
paper and let alone in my my toy example
here uh with this up we are still
considering uh relatively small graphs
the the largest graph we have considered
was 500 nodes which remains significant
you see uh important Improvement uh but
of course the the real value would come
only with uh perhaps hundreds of
thousands of notes that's when you
really need metalistics
so perhaps I didn't give um I wanted to
share this as well uh you know um an
overview of um the the kind why this
problem matters why why the traveling
Sal problem matters first theoretically
it matters because as I've said it is as
hard as any problem uh you can think of
um computationally and all NP hard
problems reduce to each other so you
could reduce you could express any NP
problem as a traveling salesman um and
also because uh it has well practical
applications it could be literally you
know determining uh um routs for for
trucks or for drones but more and more
it is um being used in in uh you know
chip design in electronic chips uh
design uh that's when you may have a
very very large number of nodes and you
need uh you know methods that are uh you
know that are progressively better at
the limit for for and tending towards
Infinity So Daniel you had an idea about
the the the theoretical grounding of the
method
well I mean just um well learn learning
from you about the this broader metah
eristic space and and seeing how this
Builds on prior work in ants
optimization and in inactive INF for
ants
um there there was just a few
interesting pieces and and um I I agree
that there could be theoretical and
empirical EXP exploration
to
uh flesh out some of the decisions that
we made here like the bigger picture on
these collective intelligence algorithms
and the reason why there's so many
species and so many different metaphors
is because there's no free lunch if the
collective behavioral algorithm
recapitulates important features of the
environment then it might be able to do
well however if it doesn't recapitulate
features of the environment then it
won't necessarily do well
so I'm thinking now about how each ant
nestmate knows the best
solution several slides I think
11 um they know their own path length
and the best path length so that's an
example of of a abstraction or a
calculation that a real ant nestmate
wouldn't necessarily
know however it might have expectations
about path lank from its own learned
experience or From
Evolution so I think that this design
space of how do we
recognize natural history and understand
what the cognitive constraints and what
the cognitive functions are in nature
for harvester ants and turtle ants and
leaf cutter ants just going to Nature
understanding what kinds of problems are
being solved and then being able to work
and Abstract that to
find slightly more generic forms of
those collective intelligence methods
that can be transferred to other
analogous
situations like more generally
collecting resources or information or
finding short paths and then what what
other elements need to come into play
and what can can situationally
supercharge the
algorithms again like having each
nestmate know at all times whether it's
itself is on a short or long path
yet Paths of real ant colonies don't
have that feature so I I just see it as
like kind of like a mechanic shop with
all these different
options and Meta Meta istics how do we
design that biological
metaphor so that it captures relevant
features of our task and
domain because there could be some
incredibly if efficient algorithms which
isn't even to say that they they would
be super
transferable but there might be some
really specific algorithms that that
could have incredible interpretability
or performance
attributes if we can select
appropriately among Collective
behavioral
algorithms what could really help here I
think um you know to to feed this this
um reflection about
what could be you know the underlying um
abstract principles that that explain
this this Improvement would be perhaps
if we could visualize the tree of you
know Solutions being explored for small
scale problems like we have here up to a
few hundred notes uh I think it would be
very interesting to to have perhaps some
uh you know colorful visualization of
basic ACO basic an Colony optimization
versus the active version and I would
really like to explore this idea you you
have mentioned which is that uh you know
this small change you make to the way uh
the probability of selecting the next
node is is calculated uh does uh you
know allow you to to escape uh
potentially you know uh not very good uh
neighborhoods so that's definitely
something we'll we'll keep in mind in
any case for this paper uh and the the
so far limited experiments we have run
one very consistent uh trend is that the
large larger the the graph the the the
higher the relative percentage of
improvements so you only see the the
real value for for large scale graphs
there is a little hiccup here for 100
node for some reason uh and I think we
had 100 graphs per per node size
so it may be because of the samples or
in any case uh we can see the trend
which is that the larger the the size of
the graph the the higher the percentage
of improvement but on the other hand and
very uh interestingly the computation
time does not increase uh proportionally
to the size of the graph in fact it
decreases so again it's it's it's not
much um adding new new operations to the
the method new you know uh new steps but
simply changing the way one operation is
done which is the the you know the the
probability of selecting the next note
uh so obviously that's going to add some
complexity but very interestingly uh
this decreases with the the size of the
the graph so it may even become
neglectable for you know very large
scale graphs where this kind of uh you
know improvements matter so the yes
please yeah I think another another
design pattern or something to explore
is having more
simpler Nest
mates versus having fewer more
cognitively sophisticated nestmates and
that's something again that that real
colonies trade off in the wild too but
now we can explore ranging from um truly
multi- threadable simple nestmates no
information sharing not even finding out
these Colony level summary
statistics super multi-thread super
paralyzable all the way on through
having more advanced Nest mates at the
per thread level but maybe they can send
each other messages or they can plan
ahead explicitly three time steps but if
they're planning ahead explicitly three
time steps and each of them is doing a
little tree roll out at each time step
it's like then the computational
complexity increases a lot and so that
space of of being able to do
sweeps across more simpler to fewer more
complicated nestmates or or cuckoo or
whatever the metaphor is and then
understand where are we getting the most
bang for the buck for a given type of
graph maybe if it's a lattice like graph
simpler colonies do better but if it's a
small world graph topology or
preferential attachment then have having
the planning capacity so that you can
know that you're going to get out of a
small neighborhood maybe that comes into
play again so it just shows that like
there isn't going to be a general
approach other than this sort of metah
heris
design level of
generality helping us articulate which
Collective behavioral methods and how
they should be tuned to bring to a given
problem so I think here there are two
points here that could be interesting uh
definitely graph um topology matters
that's something we definitely need to
explore uh whether the structure of the
graph uh you know influences the quality
of the the results you get uh and I
think for uh your first point uh which
is basically what is the the most Bare
Bones right uh population um search
method we could expl for to to really
just pinpoint what is the Improvement
brought by by active inference uh
something we could also see would be um
I think genetic algorithms evolutionary
genetic algorithms evolution is really
the the most General metaphor right for
behavior of of populations uh and there
uh you don't have information sharing uh
across Generations you just have message
transmission you know in in the genes uh
you may also have some uh Randomness
introduced by um by um mutation random
mutations that can happen and that can
help you ex you know um can help you
escape uh not very promising
neighborhoods and I think you wrote a
paper uh with C FR if I'm not mistaken
about an application of active inference
to to Evolution Daniel
right yes the variational synthesis for
Eco evoo exactly and found a very
interesting uh idea there uh again
without getting into the technicalities
it's that what can explain uh the
evolution of species or uh populations
uh could also explain you know the the
evolution of individuals so I thought
it's a very powerful idea that you have
this multi-level you know Insight uh and
that's perhaps something we could also
explore you know within the the scope of
genetic algorithm which are really just
simple model for evolution that does
perform very well for for methods for
problems like the
tsp yeah just a a short comment on that
so in cognitive Sciences the unifying
imperative is kind of like well why
should we have a separate theory of
anticipation or memory or attention why
not seek this unifying approach to model
various cognitive phenomena so now
applying that to to ecology or to
biology why why would we have one method
or analytical framework for studying
Dynamics and change within a lineage
vertical transmission and then have a
separate theory for change that happens
across lineages or communication across
lineages like in ecology so by unifying
analogy how could we look at ecosystems
as consisting of these composed
interacting components that are
changing and constituting of of
subcomponents as well how can we see all
of those processes sometimes which look
more like vertical lineage-based
transmission other times which look more
like horizontal ecological message
passing and start to look at those
overall Dynamics as part of a
unified at least measure
observation modeling approach like let's
just say we were to do um two different
colonies or two populations of
colonies and then we have them doing
different
algorithms and then we start to let that
whole thing play out we could be talking
about the variational free energy of the
nestmate within the colony the The
Colony as a collective with it best
solution the
populations and and and so on um will
that yield better explanations
predictions transferable methods that's
the question but that's the
setup yeah it would be very interesting
to to find this I think that would be
the most uh at least uh aesthetically
and you know in terms of Oram Razer um
simplest Theory it's to have something
that does apply indeed for both the
individual agents as well as the the
whole population and here another in
terms of you know elegance and and
Beauty um another thing that's uh also
um helpful is to have agents share as
little information as as uh
possible between them and also as as you
have mentioned before plan ahead as
little as as possible which also has of
course practical computational
implications you would uh you would
consume less computation uh so I think
that would be that would be useful for
that to have this unifying Theory uh
that would apply both for the behavior
of individual agents as well as the the
population as a whole so perhaps
something to explore with uh genetic
algorithms in any case for this
particular work and to
conclude uh we have shown and um we can
demonstrate it even even more potently
you know on larger scale graphs that
active inference does improve uh the
performance of population based metah
aristic uh with a very simple change
again that is very cheap computationally
uh
that may even disappear you know become
neglectable for very large scale graphs
this additional uh computational
cost uh and for future research
directions I think we have mentioned the
the main ones it's that in my opinion
the the most important one and if
there's someone to to to provide this I
think it would be yourself Daniel we
need uh better theoretical grounding for
what is going on we could definitely of
course inform that with uh you know
visualizations like I've mentioned of
the the tree of solutions and how it is
explored in in both methods but uh it
would be useful to understand how uh you
know this this enhancement uh occurs
fundamentally you know in abstract terms
uh we also need to apply it to to other
metalistics I think the best candidates
as I mentioned would be uh first genetic
algorithms but also particle swarm
optimization which has its own you know
pecularities
um we also need as I've said simpler um
you know and more barebones uh methods
this is just an engineered U belief
update uh mechanism but there is
certainly a simpler and more elegant way
to to to state the the equation
and uh to to go even Beyond uh you know
uh populationbased search and I know
that many people are working on this uh
in the active inflence Discord um what
about other multi-agent systems right
not just large language model systems
but you know in general um multi-agent
systems for robotics Etc uh could we
also improve their you know their
Collective Behavior by by including
active inference that's something I
would also love to explore
and so some some references if you are
interested in taking it further first
our paper which is on archive and also
on preprints but the advantage on print.
I is that you can listen to um podcast
in in you know in layman's term about
the the the paper so enhancing is here
you can download the AI generated
podcast to to get um
Layman's overview of the paper uh we
have also open source the whole code and
process from the beginning uh in both
our
githubsign of the repo and we have this
uh mini app active
acre. app uh
where you can uh experiment with uh you
know different solutions different parts
on real maps for example South America
here
both for you know neighborhood traveling
salesman problems as well as Global um
optimization problems and compare uh the
outcomes of both uh you know active SEO
basic SEO with the Baseline uh nearest
neighbor
so this is it for
me yeah thank you very much for the
invitation Daniel and the listeners if
any for their attention uh if you'd like
to to chat about this paper or uh you
know the integration of active inference
in general uh into uh operations
research problems or theoretical CS uh
here is my
contact thank
you awesome I'll I'll make a comment and
then read a question from the chat well
I I also really like all these
accessory
fractal all these accessory pieces to
the work the preprints and also the
replit app I I think it it also is like
kind of building out this
um Meta Meta
publication there something I learned
from you as well Daniel and one of was
that the PDF is just the beginning right
of the life cycle of research work which
is absolutely true we tend to see it as
you know the end game you got published
you got the P the PDF posted somewhere
but that's really just the beginning of
you know and uh the three fruits only
appear three five years later with the
contacts you make the discussions the
products you build on top of it so
that's definitely important yeah I I
think that's super cool and and we can
continue making that really multimedia
and accessible and rigorous so it's it's
like on that sort of dii level that's
really exciting um okay I'll ask a
question from the chat okay Bert wrote
would this approach be suited for
multivariable optimization like adding
in travel time or time
slots so multiobjective right yeah
optimiz we're talking about and here I
think uh well that's that's pretty much
my my PhD topic multiobjective
optimization so I feel very strongly
about uh about the kind of methods that
can work there uh metah eristics in
general um I mean there are different
classes of metah eristics that work
better for for multiobjective
optimization but this is definitely uh
something to explore you know
integrating active inference uh notably
to generate the as you know
multiobjective optimization problems not
have one optimal solution the even the
meaning of optimal uh is kind of mood
for multi objective problems say for
example that you have a car uh that is
evated on both its price its cost and
its performance
well what would you do if one is good
the other is not that great you would
only consider efficient Solutions right
so the main problem is to generate or
explore this front this large
potentially large set of uh solutions
that are not
dominated and uh I wouldn't make any any
guess uh about whether active inference
would work there there or whether you
know this method uh would be
translatable but uh as you as a research
product it could be really um you know a
PhD or post project to explore um the
use of active inference in uh generating
and exploring the the paral front of M
multiobjective optimization problems so
perhaps the active inference Institute
could could get something like that
going cool yeah what what comes to mind
there one would be um keeping the kernel
method the same and using program logic
to implement other constraints like
adding some day night cycle so not even
trying to make that part into active
inference but just add some secondary
logic or you know one one in every
hundred uh nodes just randomly
disappears or something like that and
then see how these metah eristics in a
in a more changing constraint setting
adapt to changes in the environment and
then the the more more fully active
inference approach would be develop more
sophisticated generative models so more
multivariable joint distributions for
nestmate and Colony perception cognition
Action Impact and then explore okay as
we bring in more joint variables into
the distribution obviously it's taking
more computational resources it's a
higher dimensional front to explore so
when and how should we pursue that full
joint distribution and then what ways
would there be to factorize it down to
solve that as a subset of linked
problems and how do we find which
subsetting and factorizing of linked
problems
allows the simplest possible nestate to
still have relevant performance and then
we we sketch out those subspaces with
parameter sweeps and
sampling yeah the reason why I think uh
you know active inference is honestly
even more promising than for um you know
single objective problems like this in
multiobjective it's that another
dimension if you have a car for example
that costs a lot but uh is performant
another one that is cheap but not that
great is that uh there is no objectively
optimal solution and there is a whole
class of methods known as interactive
methods where you try to integrate the
preferences of decision maker into the
exploration method so it is really a
person guiding the you know guiding the
the Exploration with their own
preferences and here we are touching on
you know something that uh neuroscience
and active inference is familiar with
which is uh how to integrate reasoning
and perception uh so I would be uh very
interested in exploring this reading
about it if anyone uh is inspired to to
to write about it you know how to
integrate active inference in these
interactive methods that are uh
typically used for you know exploring L
scale parto fronts yeah one one I think
footnote there for the the Curious would
be in the language model space we have
these reward reinforcement driven models
that then get tuned through human
feedback r lhf with humans giving a
raate rating or preference score so you
have the the algorithm is focusing on
maximizing satisfaction and then the
human feedback has to do with do I like
this more or less we could be exploring
some interactive optimization methods
with more
expressivity like I'm interested in
paths for the traveling salesmen that
have small turning angles and then that
would adjust the decision making if
there was a turning angle variable now
we're focusing on making that small and
then we say actually I care 20% about
the small turning angle and 80% about
short path length overall and so be able
to have this interactive blending and a
more expressive epistemic toolkit for
having interactive optimization
co-optimization and that could be really
cool or you know a part that is just
aesthetically
there are actually rooting methods in
used in tourism that try to to you know
integrate both the the the length of the
the route but if you are designing
tourists uh you know routs you also want
it to be to be pleasant so there are
definitely methods that that are applied
this way and here uh it's a remark in
general about uh single objective
optimization it's that it's always an
oversimplification when you say that
this is the one objective that that
matters uh it's never uh never fully the
case and there are always other
dimensions that can be integrated now
are percentages or you know just a
weighted sum of the objectives uh are
they enough they are more often they're
not limiting because there's a whole you
know
um a whole part of the the the part of
front that you w be able to reach with
uh a weighted sum so it's definitely
interesting to you mentioned um language
models you mentioned
uh reinforcement learning from Human
feedback uh so these are definitely
interesting approaches to integrate you
know in exploring this and in general uh
you know having a multiobjective
optimization 2.0 with all these recent
advances I think is it's solely
needed cool okay do you have any closing
comments or thoughts or well my my last
thought is that it was a very pleasant
um time I thank you very much for this
invitation and uh honestly I thought it
was just five minutes or 10 minutes of
presentation but I look at my clock and
I see that we have spent almost an hour
so it is really a rare pleasure to to
have these kind of experiences where you
don't you don't feel time anymore thank
you very much Daniel thank you awesome
okay looking forward to the next
chapters till next time thank you bye
for